William Mills Ivins
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Ivins Family Papers, 1878-1964, undated, Series 4:; (boxes 16-19; 4 linear ft.)
  - Emma Yard Ivins, 1878-1940, 4.4:
    Letters from relatives in box 18 include those from James S. Y. Ivins [son], 1897-1940; Katharine Ivins [daughter], circa 1917-1937; Margaret Ivins Holmes and Jonathan Holmes [daughter and grandson], 1909-1937; Sarah Mills Ivins [mother-in-law], 1910's; William M. Ivins, Jr. [son], 1889-1909; and William M. Ivins, Jr., and Florence Wyman Ivins [son and daughter-in-law].
    Letters from relatives in box 19 includes continued correspondence from William M. Ivins, Jr., and Florence Wyman Ivins, 1926-1940; and letters from William M. Ivins, Sr. [husband], 1883-1915; and James Sterling Yard [EYI to father], 1878.
    - Letters from friends and business correspondence, 1906-1935 (Box 18, Folder 5-6)
    - Financial correspondence, 1920-1930 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Woman's suffrage movement, 1900-1915 (Box 18, Folder 8-12)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 18, Folder 13-16)
    - Letters from relatives, 1889-1940 (Box 18, Folder 17-60)
    - Letters from relatives, 1878-1940 (Box 19, Folder 1-19)
  - Florence Wyman Ivins, circa 1911-1948, undated, 4.5:
    Florence Wyman Ivins was the wife of William M. Ivins, Jr., and an illustrator, primarily of children's books, and a painter of children's portraits. Many of her letters to family members are illustrated with pen and ink drawings or watercolors. She was addressed as Flossie of Flo.
    Letters from family and friends include those from Emma Yard Ivins [mother-in-law]; Katharine Ivins [sister-in-law]; Sarah Ivins; William M. Ivins, Jr. [husband], 1917-1928; Margaret Orr; Margaret Wind; Helen and Herbert Winlock; Wyman Family [letters from FWI to her father and sister], circa 1911-1914
    Artwork includes a sketchbook, Southold [L. I.], from the summer of 1922, containing watercolor and pencil sketches of local scenery, Barbara, WMI, Jr., Loraine Wyman, and Paderewski. Also found here are portraits of William M. Ivins, Jr, (2), Bruce Rogers, and Marion Stone; miscellaneous prints and drawings; Christmas and other greeting cards designed by FWI, circa 1910-1937, including a 1937 New Year's greeting, "A Parable of Artists and Art Critics" by Hans Christian Andersen, illustrated by FWI with calligraphy by WMI, Jr.
    Miscellaneous material includes notes about E.S. [Elizabeth Sears?]; a flyer advertising children's portraits by FWI, with snapshots of children [used for paintings?]; a marriage announcement and related clippings, 1910; and Wyman family obituaries, including FWI.
    Writings include childhood reminiscences and principles of art instruction at Brearly School.
    - Letters from family and friends, circa 1911-1948 (Box 19, Folder 20-23)
    - Artwork (Box 19, Folder 24-28)
    - Miscellaneous Material (Box 19, Folder 29-31)
    - Writings, undated (Box 19, Folder 32-33)
  - Katharine Ivins 1890s-1962, undated, 4.6:
    Katharine Ivins (circa 1888-) was the sister of William M.Ivins, Jr. A music teacher, she lived with mother in the Yard family home, in Freehold, N.J. She was addressed as Kate or Katti.
    Letters from relatives include those from Barbara Ivins [niece], 1926, 1962; Florence Wyman Ivins [sister-in-law], circa 1918-1947; Margaret Ivins Holmes [sister], undated; and William M. Ivins, Jr. [brother], 1928-1961. Writings include an essay [school homework], circa 1890's?], and a notebook, including childhood reminiscences with mention of mother's photography, schooling etc.
    - Letters from relatives, 1890's-1962 (Box 19, Folder 34-46)
    - Letters from friends, business, 1910's, undated (Box 19, Folder 47)
    - Writings, undated (Box 19, Folder 48-49)
  - Margaret Ivins Holmes, 1890s-1954, 4.7:
    Margaret Ivins Holmes, (1882-1954), sister of William M. Ivins, Jr., lived in Freehold, N.J. and ran an antique store there with her husband, William Holmes. She was addressed as Margie or Peggy. Letters from relatives include those from Florence W. Ivins [sister-in-law]; William M. Ivins, Jr. [brother]; and William M. Ivins, Sr. [father].
    - Letters from relatives, 1890's-1954 (Box 19, Folder 50)
  - Sarah Mills Ivins, 1890s-1910, 4.8:
    - Letters from Emma Yard Ivins [daughter-in-law], and William M. Ivins, Jr. [grandson], 1890's-1910 (Box 19, Folder 51)
  - William M. Ivins, Sr., 1891-1924, 4.9:
    William M. Ivins, Sr., (1851-1915), father of William M. Ivins, Jr., was a lawyer and politician and was addressed as Will. He spent a great deal of time in Europe and South America as a corporate lawyer. In 1905, he ran unsuccessfully for mayor of New York City. Business correspondence includes a letter from Mme. Blavatsky, with clippings and photographic portrait. Letters from relatives include those from Emma Yard Ivins [wife], 1904; Katharine Ivins [daughter], 1901; Margaret Ivins Holmes [daughter], 1901; Sarah Mills Ivins [mother]; William M. Ivins, Jr. [son], 1891-1902; Annie Perrine [cousin]; James S. Yard [father-in-law]. Miscellaneous material includes biographical notes; clippings by and about WMI Sr., 1897-1915, including an obituary; and miscellaneous notes copied from an unidentified publication.
    - Business correspondence, 1897-1901 (Box 19, Folder 52-53)
    - Letters from relatives, 1891-1915 (Box 19, Folder 54-59)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 19, Folder 60-62)
    - Estate correspondence, 1914-1924 (Box 19, Folder 63)
- Photographs, circa 1890-1940, undated, Series 5:; (boxes 21-21; 2 linear ft.)
  In addition to portraits of family members this series includes interior and exterior views of homes, and pictures of friends and events.
  The series is organized into three subseries:
  5.1: Family Photographs, circa 1890-1905
  5.2: Photographs of Architecture by WMI, Jr., circa 1930-1940
  5.3: Miscellaneous Photographs, undated
  - Family Photographs, 5.1:
    The Ivins Family photographs represent many processes from tintypes to silver gelatin prints. A number were taken by accomplished amateur photographer Emma Yard Ivins of her children, circa 1890-1905; a few of her children are purported to be the work of Gertrude Kasebier (possibly an acquaintance of Emma Yard Ivins?).
    Family photographs folders are labelled with the name of an individual or family, and arranged alphabetically; within each folder, photographs are arranged in rough chronological order. Portraits of individuals are filed by name and group shots are filed by the name of the family; childhood pictures are filed under the parents' family. (For example, pictures of Emma Yard Ivins as a child are filed under the name Yard and any group shots she appears in will be found under the name James S. and Adaline Swift Yard Family; group shots of her after marriage are included with the pictures of the William M. Jr. and Emma Yard Ivins Family).
    Photographs of William M. Ivins, Jr., and the Florence Wyman family include their New York City apartment, summer house in Westport, Conn., and their Woodbury, Conn. home in addition to photographs of them with friends Bryson Burroughs, Naum Gabo, Walter Hauser, A. Hyatt Mayor, Peyton Rous, Rudolph Ruzicka, Mahonri Young, and unidentified.
    - Ivins, Barbara (1913-), circa 1890-1905 (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
    - Ivins, Emma Yard (1857-1940), circa 1890-1905 (Box 20, Folder 3-4)
      (includes Yard Family home, Freehold, N.J.)
    - Ivins, Florence Wyman (1881-1948), circa 1890-1905 (Box 20, Folder 5-7)
      (includes photos of illustrations by FWI)
    - Ivins, Katharine (c. 1888-), circa 1890-1905 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Ivins, Margaret [Holmes] (1882-1954), circa 1890-1905 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Ivins, Sarah Mills (1832-1914), circa 1890-1905 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Ivins, William M., Jr. (1881-1961), circa 1890-1905 (Box 20, Folder 11-12)
    - Ivins, William M., Jr. and Florence Wyman Family, circa 1890-1905 (Box 20, Folder 13-20)
    - Ivins, William M., Sr. (1851-1915), circa 1890-1905 (Box 20, Folder 21)
    - Ivins, William M., Sr. and Emma Yard Family, circa 1890-1905 (Box 20, Folder 22-24)
      (including views of The Hut and The Breezes, Narragansett Pier, R.I.)
    - Mills, William T. (1811-), circa 1890-1905 (Box 20, Folder 25)
    - Wyman, Loraine (-1937), circa 1890-1905 (Box 20, Folder 26)
    - Yard, James Sterling (1826-1900) and Adaline Swift (1837-1912) Family (1826-1912), circa 1890-1905 (Box 20, Folder 27)
    - Yard, Mary Sterling (1805-1863), circa 1890-1905 (Box 20, Folder 28)
    - Unidentified People, circa 1890-1905 (Box 20, Folder 29-30)
  - Architecture Photographs, circa 1930-1940, 5.2:
    Architecture photographs mainly consist of photographs of colonial architecture, apparently taken by William M. Ivins circa 1930-1940. These are unidentified, except for location, and arranged by state. Also included are a few scenes of Europe from the same period, featuring buildings.
    - Europe, circa 1930-1940 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Connecticut, circa 1930-1940 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Maryland, circa 1930-1940 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Massachussetts, circa 1930-1940 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - New Hampshire, circa 1930-1940 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - New York, circa 1930-1940 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Pennsylvania, circa 1930-1940 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Rhode Island, circa 1930-1940 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - South Carolina (Charleston), circa 1930-1940 (Box 21, Folder 9-10)
    - Vermont, circa 1930-1940 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Virginia, circa 1930-1940 (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified locations [New England and elsewhere], circa 1930-1940 (Box 21, Folder 13-14)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, undated, 5.3:
    Miscellaneous photographs include those used as illustrations for How Prints Look and pictures of the Alberti Model for On the Rationalization of Sight (which may have been used to illustrate other writings, as well). The subseries also includes additional subjects such as a view of the Swarthmore College campus [Barbara's alma mater] and painting conservation [Metropolitan Museum of Art?].
    - Illustrations for How Prints Look, undated (Box 21, Folder 15-18)
    - Alberti Model, illustration for On the Rationalization of Sight, undated (Box 21, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous Subjects, undated (Box 21, Folder 20)
- Oversize Material, 1897-1950, Series 6:; (1 OV folder)
  - St. Paul's School Diploma, July 9, 1897 (Box 22 (ov))
  - Harvard College Diploma, June 27, 1901 (Box 22 (ov))
  - Columbia College School of Law Diploma, June 12, 1907 (Box 22 (ov))
  - Yale University, Honorary Doctorate Diploma, Nov. 14, 1946 (Box 22 (ov))
  - St. Paul's School, achievement award, July 9, 1897 (Box 22 (ov))
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, honorary fellow, May 20, 1946 (Box 22 (ov))
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, fellow, May 1, 1950 (Box 22 (ov))
  - U.S. Passport, September 24, 1901 (Box 22 (ov))